<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Project Euler - Ruby | Elegant Development]]></title>
  <link href="http://tibsar.github.io/blog/categories/project-euler-ruby/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tibsar.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-29T16:00:43-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://tibsar.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sara Tibbetts]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Project Euler #2 - Ruby]]></title>
    <link href="http://tibsar.github.io/blog/project-euler-number-2-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-28T15:31:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tibsar.github.io/blog/project-euler-number-2-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Time for the second Project Euler post!</p>

<h2>Project Euler #2</h2>

<blockquote><p>Each new term in the Fibonacci sequence is generated by adding the previous two terms. By starting with 1 and 2, the first 10 terms will be:</p>

<p>1, 2, 3, 5, 8, 13, 21, 34, 55, 89, ...</p>

<p>By considering the terms in the Fibonacci sequence whose values do not exceed four million, find the sum of the even-valued terms. <cite>Project Euler #2</cite></p></blockquote>

<p>So it looks like we need to find all of the even numbers in the Fibonacci sequence, and then add them all together.</p>

<h3>Calculating the Fibonacci Sequence</h3>

<p>It seems like a good place to start would be finding the Fibonacci Sequence up to the limit specified by the question.  The next number in the sequence is found by adding the previous two terms.  The question shows that the sequence starts with 1 (actually, it starts with 0 followed by two ones, but we'll follow the problem) and the following number is 2.  We'll specify our starting points in the code.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">num = 2 
previous_num = 1
new_num = num + previous_num
</code></pre>

<p>The code above will set <code>new_num</code> to <code>2 + 1</code> which is <code>3</code>, the next number in the sequence.  However, this code can only ever find the next number after the first two numbers.  We're going to want to keep going until we hit the limit. This seems like the perfect time for an <code>until</code> loop.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby ">num = 2 
previous_num = 1
until num &gt;= limit 
    new_num = num + previous_num
end 
</code></pre>

<p>Now this code has a few problems.  First, <code>limit</code> is never defined.  We can fix that by wrapping our code in a function that has the limit as a parameter.
<code>ruby
def even_fibonacci_sum(limit)
    num = 2
    previous_num = 1
    until num &gt;= limit
        new_num = num + previous_num
    end
end
</code>
Our code still has a major issue.  The loop will continue forever since we are never changing the value of <code>num</code>.  Since we also don't change the value of <code>previous_num</code>, <code>new_num</code> will always be three, so this code doesn't get us any further in the Fibonacci sequence.  We need to update the <code>previous_num</code> as well as the current <code>num</code> in order to keep going in the sequence.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby ">def even_fibonacci_sum(limit)
    num = 2 
    previous_num = 1
    until num &gt;= limit 
        new_num = num + previous_num
        previous_num = num
        num = new_num
    end 
end
</code></pre>

<p>Now we're finding all numbers in the Fibonacci sequence up to the limit!</p>

<h3>Calculating the Sum</h3>

<p>Finding all the numbers in the Fibonacci sequence up to the limit is great, but we're not actually doing anything with those numbers.  The problem specifies that we're going to ultimately want the sum of the even numbers, so we should probably keep track of that as we go along.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby ">def even_fibonacci_sum(limit)
    num = 2 
    previous_num = 1
    sum = 0
    until num &gt;= limit 
    if num.even?
        sum += num
    end 
        new_num = num + previous_num
        previous_num = num
        num = new_num
    end 
end
</code></pre>

<p>So now we check if the nummber is even and if it is, add it to our sum, all we need to do now is make sure we return that sum, which in Ruby is generally done implicitely.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby ">def even_fibonacci_sum(limit)
    num = 2 
    previous_num = 1
    sum = 0
    until num &gt;= limit 
    if num.even?
        sum += num
    end 
        new_num = num + previous_num
        previous_num = num
        num = new_num
    end 
    sum
end
</code></pre>

<h3>Arriving at a Solution</h3>

<p>To get the solution, run your code! In the terminal, running <code>ruby file_name_here.rb</code> with whatever you named the file that you are coding in, will display the soluton to the terminal screen.  When you think you have a solution, you make sure to submit it <a href="https://projecteuler.net/problem=2" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<p>If you feel that you have a better solution, post a gist to it in the comments!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Project Euler #1 - Ruby]]></title>
    <link href="http://tibsar.github.io/blog/project-euler-number-1-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-19T07:11:32-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tibsar.github.io/blog/project-euler-number-1-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am going to start solving all of the Project Euler problems on my blog.  This will take an incredibly long time, but I believe that it's a great warm up for coding. So that being said, there's no better place to begin than with number 1.</p>

<h2>Project Euler #1</h2>

<blockquote><p>If we list all the natural numbers below 10 that are multiples of 3 or 5, we get 3, 5, 6, and 9.  The sum of these multiples is 23.<br/>
Find the sum of all the multiples of 3 or 5 below 1000. <cite>Project Euler #1</cite></p></blockquote>

<p>After reading the problem, I have a basic understanding of what I need to do.  I need to first find all of the multiples or either 3 or 5 that are less than 1000.  Once I have those multiples, I need to add them all together to get my solution.</p>

<h3>Collecting the Multiples</h3>

<p>First I need to find all of the multiples under 1000.  In order to do that I have to know what makes a number a multiple or 3 or 5. A great way to tell is if the number in question divided by either 3 or 5 results in a whole number with no remainder.  If this is true, the number is evenly divisible by either 3 or 5 and a multiple. I know that Ruby has a great function for checking for remainders called modulo.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">(number_in_question % 3 == 0) || (number_in_question % 5 == 0)
</code></pre>

<p>This code will return <code>true</code> if the <code>number_in_question</code> is a multiple of 3 or 5.  However, we stil have no way of finding the <code>number_in_question</code>.</p>

<p>The problem gives us a hint at where to start for this part.  The problem is asking for all multiples that are below 1000.  Therefore, we need to check all numbers below 1000. That suggests that we need to use an exclusive range.  So to collect all of the numbers below 1000 in an array we can do the following:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby ">limit = 1000
(1...limit).to_a
</code></pre>

<p>However, this will collect all of the numbers below 1000, and we only want the numbers that are multiples of 3 or 5.  To do this, we can use the select method.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby ">(1...limit).select{ |i| (i % 5 == 0 || i % 3 == 0)}
</code></pre>

<p>This will only select numbers that are less than 1000 but a multiple of either 3 or 5 and store them in an array.  Let's turn it into a function, so that it is easily accessible for our next step.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby ">def collect_multiples(limit)
  (1...limit).select{ |i| (i % 5 == 0 || i % 3 == 0)}
end 
</code></pre>

<h3>Adding the Multiples Together</h3>

<p>Now that we have access to an array of all the multiples we want, all we have to do is add them together. Luckily, Ruby has a great function to help us out. The <code>reduce</code> function will allow us to perform an operation on all of the items in an array. So to find the sum of the multiples this is all we have to do:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">collect_multiples(1000).reduce(:+)
</code></pre>

<h3>Arriving at a Solution</h3>

<p>We've done all the coding necessary to find the solution!  Now I don't want to give it away, so I'm not going to post it here, but if you're unsure if your code works or not, look at the example in the problem. Use 10 as your limit and try to get 23 as a result.  When you think you have a solution, you can sign up for a Project Euler account and submit it <a href="https://projecteuler.net/problem=1" target="_blank">here</a>. Here's some proof that this code works:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://i.imgur.com/SEiCPvl.png">
And if you want to see all the code in one place:
<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">collect_multiples</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">limit</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">.</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">limit</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">select</span><span class="p">{</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="o">|</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">i</span> <span class="o">%</span> <span class="mi">5</span> <span class="o">==</span> <span class="mi">0</span> <span class="o">||</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="o">%</span> <span class="mi">3</span> <span class="o">==</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">)}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="sr">/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sr">&lt;p&gt;puts collect_multiples(1000).reduce(:+)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></p>

<p>In the terminal, running <code>ruby file_name_here.rb</code> with whatever you named the file that you are coding in, will display the soluton to the terminal screen.</p>

<p>If you feel that you have a better solution, post a gist to it in the comments!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
